Guide to the Burt Green Wilder papers, 1841-1925
Wilder, Burt Green papers, 1841-1925
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Burt Green Wilder papers, 1841-1925
14-26-95
Burt G. (Burt Green) Wilder, 1841-1925
7 cubic ft.
Correspondence, manuscripts, clippings, diaries, photographs.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Diaries; notes and charts pertaining to family genealogy; clippings concerning vivisection; correspondence, photographs, and printed material pertaining to spiders, phrenology, hygiene and education, writing music, Nantucket Island, the Field family, Oliver Wendell Holmes, Sr., temperance, natural history, Wilder's career as a medical cadet and military surgeon during the Civil War; activities of members of the 54th and 55th Massachusetts Infantry and the 5th Massachusetts Cavalry both during and after the war, Negro troops, his training under Louis Agassiz, Asa Gray, and Jeffries Wyman, and his career as a professor at Cornell University.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Neurologist, professor of anatomy, comparative neurology, and zoology at Cornell University.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
These papers consist of correspondence with colleagues and friends; personal prose and poetry; Civil War correspondence and history with papers and clippings re Burt Green Wilder's career and service as a medical cadet at the Judiciary Square Hospital in Washington, D.C. in 1862, and as assistant surgeon (First Lieutenant), 1863, and then surgeon of the Massachusetts 55th Black Volunteer Regiment until 1865. After the Civil War and for the rest of his life, BGW actively corresponded with veterans of the war, both Yankee and Confederate. There are letters and clippings re pension requests, commission papers, discharge and parole papers, treatment of prisoners from both the North and South; a history of black soldiers; federal government segregation; clippings and letters re battles such as River's Causeway, Fort Wagner, the siege of Charleston, Grimball's Causeway, Fort Sumter, Honey Hill, Pocotaligo and Folly Island. (While he was stationed at Folly Island in 1863, BGW discovered a large spider later named the NEPHILA WILDERI, from which at a later time he reeled off 150 yards of yellow silk.) An account of "The 55th Massachusetts Volunteer Infantry, Colored", written by BGW and given as a address before the Brookline, Massachusetts Historical Society on May 28, 1914; and letters and clippings re the death and burial of Col. Robert Gould Shaw of the Massachusetts 54th Volunteers with his fallen black troops at the battle of Fort Wagner on July 18, 1863, and clippings re the Shaw Monument in the Boston Common by Augustus St. Gaudens are also included. Other Civil War reminiscences include BGW's Civil War diary, 1863-1865; letters and newspaper clippings re Lt. George T. Garrison (eldest son of William Lloyd Garrison), General Sam Jones, Robertson James (brother of Henry James), Lt. Col. Charles B. Fox, Capt. Charles C. Soule, Capt. Wheelock Pratt, Francis H. Brown, M.D., James F.A. Allen, M.D., Rev. James H. Fowler, Luis F. Emilio, Col. Robert Gould Shaw, Col. Norwood Penrose Hallowell (Commander of the 55th Massachusetts Volunteer Regiment), Col. John L. Clem (the youngest soldier to serve with the Union Army), Gen. William T. Sherman, Jefferson Davis, and many others.
These papers also contain correspondence with Prof. Louis Agassiz (the naturalist), Asa Gray, Oliver Wendell Holmes, Sr., and Jeffries Wyman, with whom BGW worked at Harvard University as an assistant after receiving his M.D. degree there in 1866. There are letters, papers, clippings and various medical pamphlets from BGW's years as a professor of anatomy, physiology, comparative neurology and vertebrate zoology at Cornell from 1867-1910, where he devoted special attention to human and animal brain mechanism experiments, and the nervous system. At the time of his retirement he had gathered between 1,600 and 2,000 brain specimens with completed data. (Currently, 70 of these specimens survive.) The collection also contains "Brain Bequest" forms, and letters dealing with the reneged brain bequest of Goldwin Smith; papers relating to BGW's laboratory studies of cats (possibly as many as 400 cats per year were used for these studies) and other "wild" animals such as opossums (including many others.)
At the end of twenty-five years of teaching, Professor Wilder was presented with "The Wilder Quarter Century Book" (a festschrift). This was a collection of original papers dedicated to him by former students in 1893.
Also, female and male spider (NEPHILA WILDERI) specimens and 2 mile silk strand.
Right ulna bone fragments of Daniel P. Havey of the 19th Mass. Infantry Regiment, 1862 (with shot).
SUBJECTS:
Names:
Adams, J. F. A.; Agassiz, Elizabeth Cabot Cary, 1822-1907.; Agassiz, George R. (George Russell), b. 1862; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873.; Agassiz, R. L.; Allen, Harrison, 1841-1897.; Bean, Arthur.; Bean, Robert Bennett, 1874-1944; Burr, George Lincoln, 1857-1938.; Carnegie, Andrew, 1835-1919.; Codman, John.; Comstock, Anna Botsford, 1854-1930.; Comstock, John Henry, 1849-1931.; Corson, Eugene Rollin, b. 1855.; Corson, Hiram, 1828-1911.; Curtis, George William, 1824-1892.; Deland, Margaret Wade Campbell, 1857-1945.; Drew, Alice.; Eliot, Charles William, 1834-1926.; Gage, Simon Henry, 1851-1944.; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888.; Herrick, Clarence Luther, 1858-1904.; Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1809-1894.; Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1841-1935.; Holt, Henry, 1840-1926.; Howells, William Dean, 1837-1920.; Humphrey, G. M.; Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1825-1895.; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931.; Kellog, John Harvey.; Lamb, D. S.; Minot, Charles Sedgwick, 1852-1914.; Reed, H.D. (Hugh Daniel), 1875-1937.; Schurman, Jacob Gould, 1854-1942.; Seaman, Louis Livingston, 1851-1932.; Smith, Goldwin, 1823-1910.; Spitzka, Edward A.; Spitzka, E. C. (Edward Charles), 1852-1914; Van Dyke, Henry, 1852-1933.; Wilder, Burt Green, 1841-1925. Wilder quarter century book.; Wyman, Jeffries, 1864-; Field family.; Cornell University--Faculty.; Cornell University--Students.; Cornell University. Dept. of Zoology.; United States. Army. Massachusetts Infantry Regiment, 54th (1863-1865).; United States. Army. Massachusetts Infantry Regiment, 55th (1863-1865).; United States. Army. Massachusetts Cavalry Regiment, 5th (1862-1865).
Subjects:
Brain.; College students.; Composition (Music).; Education.; Hygiene.; Natural history.; Neurology.; Phrenology.; Racism.; Science--Study and teaching.; Sex instruction.; Silk.; Spiders.; Temperance.; Vivisection.; College teachers.; Neurologists.; Surgeons.; Physicians.
Places:
Nantucket Island (Mass.); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--African Americans.
Form and Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Genealogies.; Notebooks.; Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
See also the Department of Zoology Records, #14-26-966, http://resolver.library.cornell.edu/cgi-bin/EADresolver?id=RMA00966
See also the Albert Hazen Wright papers, #14-26-1382, http://resolver.library.cornell.edu/cgi-bin/EADresolver?id=RMA01382
CONTAINER LIST
- Letters from Asa Gray, Elliot Coues and others. Also, museum item descriptions of Dr. Paul B. DuChaillu's African collection and a seaman's "relief and protection" agreement. January 22 1841, July 7, 1849 - August 21, 1866, 1841-1866 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Letters from A.D. White, Major John W. M. Appleton, Louis Agassiz, Dr. Asa Gray, Mary A. Quincy Gould (daughter of Josiah Quincy and wife of Benjamin A. Gould), Oliver Wendell Holmes, Sr., Edward Everett Hale, Dr. Harrison Allen, Eliza Susan Quincy, George William Curtis and others., Sept. 4, 1866-Nov. 25, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Letters from W.P. Samson, Elizabeth C. Agassiz, James Dwight Dana, Oliver Wendell Holmes, Wendell Phillips Garrison, Jeffries Wyman, Louis Agassiz, and others., Jan. 22, 1870-Jan. 16, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Letters from Goldwin Smith, Oliver Wendell Holmes, Elizabeth Agassiz (Mrs. Louis Agassiz), and Louis Agassiz, (including the letter Agassiz wrote to BGW asking him to accept a position at the Harvard Museum of Comparative Zoology)., Apr. 1, 1872-May 30, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Letters from Jeffries Wyman, William Dean Howells, Asa Gray, Elizabeth C. Agassiz, Oliver Wendell Holmes, Sir Richard Owen, George Rolleston, Charles Darwin, James Dwight Dana, Simon Henry Gage., June 17, 1874-Nov. 25, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Harrison Allen, Oliver Wendell Holmes, Sir Richard Owen, Simon Henry Gage, Dr. William Parker., Jan. 11, 1877-Dec. 19, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Letters from Leland Ossian Howard, Thomas Dwight, Oliver Wendell Holmes, Simon Henry Gage, Spencer Fullerton Baird, and others., Jan. 16, 1881- Apr. 25, 1882 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Dr. Louis L. Seaman, Wendell Phillips Garrison, Oliver Wendell Holmes, Elliot Coues, David Starr Jordan, J. W. Slater, Theodore Gill and others., May 3, 1882-Nov. 15, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Simon Henry Gage, Joseph Leidy, Charles M. Tyler, Harrison Allen, and others., Jan. 15, 1884-Nov. 18, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Edward Drinker Cope, Simon Henry Gage, Oliver Wendell Holmes, William A. Sprague, Sir Richard Owen, Harrison Allen, Alexander Graham Bell., Apr. 12, 1887-Jan. 27, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- William Dean Howells, Simon Henry Gage, Joseph Leidy, Charles M. Tyler, Harrison Allen, Othniel Charles Marsh., Feb. 26, 1889-Dec. 20, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Thomas Henry Huxley, Harrison Allen, Mary Gage Day, James Thurber, E. L. Williams, Goldwin Smith, Simon Henry Gage., Jan. 11, 1890-Dec. 23, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Goldwin Smith, Harrison Allen, Charles Sedgwick Minot, Flavel S. Thomas, M.D., John Henry Comstock, Simon Henry Gage, Pierre A. Fish, Theobald Smith, Hermann M. Briggs, Elizabeth C. Agassiz, George Lincoln Burr, Dr. William Browning., Jan. 1, 1892-May 29, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- John Henry Comstock, Charles Sedgwick Minot, William Parker, Harrison Allen, Andrew D. White, Dr. Theobald Smith, W.R. Dudley, Elizabeth C. Agassiz, David Starr Jordan, George M. Gould, Jacob Gould Schurman, Oliver Wendell Holmes, George R. Williams, William Channing Russell and others., June 23, 1883-Nov. 28, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Charles Sedgwick Minot, Andrew Carnegie, Harrison Allen, George M. Gould, Oliver Wendell Holmes Jr., William Clark Russell, William Russel Dudley, and others., Dec. 21, 1893-Apr. 7, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Letters from Andrew Sloan Draper, Frank Collins Baker, Simon Henry Gage, Dr. Harrison Allen (correspondence with Dr. Allen and newspaper clippings of his obituary), and others. Also, one photograph of Donald McGee, an infant whose brain was used for BGW's collection filed with four letters to Wilder from his mother Dr. Anita Newcomb McGee., June 11, 1895-Nov. 17, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Letters from Frank Collins Baker, George W. Allen, and others. Also, a biographical sketch and tribute written by Burt Green Wilder for Dr. Harrison Allen. Included in this folder is a military record of Harrison Allen's service in the Civil War., Dec. 1897 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Letters from Goldwin Smith, Simon Henry Gage, Harrison Allen Jr., Elizabeth C. Agassiz, Samuel Eliot, George W. Gould and others. Included is a memoir of Dr. Harrison Allen, and several newspaper clippings., Jan. 4, 1898-Oct. 27, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Letters from Simon Henry Gage, Edward Everett Hale, Francis Greenwood Peabody, George Milbry Gould, Dr. Matthew Woods, Elizabeth Cady Stanton (a document re the disposition of her brain from BGW's collection); Paul B. DuChaillu, J.B.Howes, Jacob Gould Schurman, C.L. Herrick, Elizabeth C. Agassiz, Goldwin Smith, and others., Nov. 15, 1898-Nov. 10, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Newspaper clippings, various correspondence. Also, letters from George MilbryGould, Simon Henry Gage, Jacob Gould Schurman, Elizabeth C. Agassiz and Goldwin Smith’s brain bequest., February 28, 1902-Nov. 29, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- One article: "Some Intellectual Weeds of American Growth," by George M. Gould, M.D.; several acknowledgements for "The Quarter Century Book," letters from Andrew D. White, Elizabeth C. Agassiz, Jeffries Wyman, George Lincoln Burr, and others., Dec. 17, 1903-Feb. 13, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Letters from Charles W. Elliot, Eugene Rollin Corson, Frank A. Barton, Jeffries Wyman, Goldwin Smith, W.P. Garrison, George M. Gould, Julia Ward Howe, Wendell Phillips Garrison. Also, some newspaper clippings., Mar. 12, 1905-May 23, 1906 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Letters from George M. Gould, Wendell Phillips Garrison, (Including his obituary), Henry Holt, Samuel McChord Crothers, Jacob Gould Schurman, Glover Morrill Allen, G.R. Agassiz., June 27, 1906-July 23, 1907 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Letters from A. Agassiz, William Lloyd Garrison, G.R. Agassiz, Goldwin Smith, Glover Morrill Allen, Phillip McK. Garrison, William Winter, Francis Greenwood Peabody, Henry Holt, and others., July 29, 1907-Feb. 25, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- George Milbry Gould, Thomas Dwight, George Hodges, Goldwin Smith (some of his last letters to Burt Green Wilder), Henry Holt, William Winter, and various other correspondence., Mar. 6, 1908-May 11, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Letters from William Elliot Griffis, William Winter, R.L. Agassiz, Hiram Corson, Andrew Carnegie, John Henry Comstock, Andrew D. White, Thomas Dwight. Several newspaper articles and also correspondence re the disposition of Goldwin Smith's brain., May 16, 1910-Dec, 31, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Letters from David Starr Jordan, Charles W. Eliot, Andrew D. White, Charles Alexander and others. Also included are typescript copies of letters written by Burt Green Wilder., Jan. 6, 1911 Sept. 29, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Letters to and from BGW mainly dealing with his writing and musical compositions such as the music he wrote for Joyce Kilmer's poem, "The Peacemaker.", Nov. 18, 1912-Feb. 24, 1913 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Reprints of published articles and a typescript career resume of Vladimir Karapetoff., Feb. 1913? (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Various correspondence including some from men who served in the 54th Massachusetts Volunteer Regiment under Col. Robert Shaw., Mar. 3, 1913-Feb. 17, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Letters from E. B. Titchener, W. Tecumseh Sherman, Charles W. Eliot, Robert T. Morris, F.P. Sprague and others. There are also letters dealing with racial questions, miscegenation, and the Oliver Wendell Holmes poem, "Old Ironsides.", Mar. 19, 1914-Feb. 19, 1916 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Letters from David Starr Jordan, Charles W. Eliot and others., Apr. 15, 1916 - Jan. 31, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Letters from Elizabeth C. Agassiz, Alice H. James, David Starr Jordan, Katharine Lee Bates, Henry Smith Pritchett and others., Feb. 2, 1917- Sept. 25, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- John Haynes Holmes, R.S. Woodward, Albert Bushnell Hart, Edward A. Horton, Marquise Clara Lanza, and others., Oct. 1, 1917-May 17, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Copy of a letter of Louis Agassiz, Samuel Atkins Eliot, Henry Cabot Lodge, Aline Kilmer, Henry Holt, Henry van Dyke, and others., June 27, 1918-May 27, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Oliver Wendell Holmes Jr., Simon Henry Gage, Aline Kilmer (Mrs. Joyce Kilmer), Edward W. Emerson, and others., June 2, 1919-Nov. 29, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Letters to and from Burt Green Wilder; also newspaper clippings., Dec. 16, 1919-May 28, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Letters from Joyce Kilmer, John Henry Comstock, Walter R. Spaulding and others., June 2, 1920-Dec. 21, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Letters from Oliver Wendell Holmes, Anna Comstock, Edward W. Emerson, Henry van Dyke, and others. Also included are typescript copies of letters written by BGW., Jan. 22, 1921-July 14, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Letters to and from BGW mainly dealing with his writing and musical compositions such as the music he wrote for Joyce Kilmer's poem, "The Peacemaker.", Oct. 26, 1921-Nov. 27, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Letters of condolence re Mrs. Wilder's death; music written by BGW for "The Peacemaker," expressions of concern for BGW's ill health; the Louis Agassiz Memorial exercises at the Marine Biological Laboratory at Wood's Hole, Mass.; other letters from colleagues and friends. October 17, 1922 - February 28, 1925, August 14, 1933, 1922-1933 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Letters from Elizabeth C. Agassiz; Walter F. Willcox, Samuel A. Eliot, portion of a letter from Louis Agassiz, (very faded); George R. Kennedy, Frank W. Very and others., Undated letters (Box 3, Folder 16)
- "Immortality and Sir Oliver Lodge" by William Dean Howells; Letters from Sir Richard Owen, Elizabeth C. Agassiz. Morrill Wyman; W.R. Spalding, W. Newton Parker, Samuel A. Eliot, William Russel Dudley, and others., Undated items and letters (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Biographical Sketch of Burt Green Wilder. (From the Boston Globe)., Sept. 1, 1912 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- A history of Black Soldiers. (Extract from a lecture, 1910). Also, letters and one newspaper clipping, 1913, 1917-1919., 1910, 1913, 1917-1919 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Boy Scout "find" at Yellow Bluff, Florida, of Confederate items. Sent to Wilder from John Gordon., 1920 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Recollections of a Civil War expedition of February 28, 1865 by Major R.J. Hamilton., Aug. 28, 1913 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Clippings re Col. John L. Clem, the youngest soldier to serve in the Union army., 1912-1913 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Commission Papers of Burt Green Wilder., 1862-63, 1865-66, 1885 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Letters to B.G.W. from Confederate Soldiers., 1895, 1897, 1901-02, 1912-1917 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Clipping from the Confederate Veteran re the Ku-Klux Klan., July, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Letters to BGW from men who served with Company 1, 103rd New York., 1913-14 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Discharge papers and Parole forms., 1862, 1865 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Military Order of the Loyal Legion of the United States., 1901 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- "Extra Digits," by BGW. Reprinted from the Massachusetts Medical Society., June 2, 1868 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Address given by BGW on the "Fifty-fifth Massachusetts Volunteer Infantry, Colored," before the Brookline, Massachusetts Historical Society., May 28, 1914 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Letters of thanks to BGW for his research and publication on the 55th Massachusetts Colored Regiment.", Aug. 14, 1917-Mar. 22, 1919 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Letters to BGW from, and about the 54th and 55th Massachusetts Regiment Enlisted Men., 1914, 1917-18, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Correspondence re the pay of 54th and 55th Massachusetts Volunteers., 1909-1910 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Obituary of Col. Norwood Penrose Hallowell, 1912? (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Hospitals in Washington, D.C., during the Civil War., 1863, 1902, 1913 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Typescript sketch and hand sketched and printed maps of James Island, South Carolina., c. 1888 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Letters from Emily Read Jones re her father's book on the Siege of Charleston. (Daughter of General Sam Jones)., 1912-1913 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Correspondence with R.E. Mellichamp (an Episcopal minister), including a hand drawn map of James Island and surrounding areas., 1913 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- "Proposed Arrangement of Specimens of a Single Structure for Museums," by Thomas Dwight. (One reprint)., May, 1903 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Miscellaneous items. Includes shoulder stripes., 1865-1915 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- The Neale Advertiser on Civil War books. (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Recollections of individuals who served aboard the S. S. Pawnee., 1914 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Letter to The New York Evening Post from T.W. Higginson (Col. 1st South Carolina regiment) re the lower pay given to black Civil War troops., Oct. 1904 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Pension requests for families of Civil War soldiers., 1916-1917 (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Transfered (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Wilder "Quarter Century Book." (BGW's 25 years of service at Cornell.), 1868-1893 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Obituary of BGW from The Ithaca Journal., Jan. 25, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 30)
- Letters and recollections of Sgt. Andrew Jackson Smith, African-American member of the Massachusetts 55th Regiment (Box 4, Folder 31)
- Andersonville (newspaper clippings)., May 1916 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- The Shaw Monument in the Boston Common (and other clippings re Robert Gould Shaw)., 1913-1915 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Letters re the Burial of Colonel Robert Shaw from General George P. Harrison., 1915 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Soldiers' First Free Library and Reading Room-Elida and John Fowle., 1863, 1915 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Fort Sumter, as it was during the effects of the bombardment., 1863-1865 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Letters in answer to BGW's questions on Civil War reminiscences from veterans., 1886-1917 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Extracts from the Diary of George T. Garrison., 1864-1865 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Manuscript memorial of Frank Goodwin, by Major Luis F. Emilio., Oct. 20, 1895 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Johns Island Demonstration., Feb. 8-11, 1864 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Letters re allegations of misconduct by Yankee soldiers made by Mr. Mazyck Porcher., 1912-1913 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Letters re The Battle of Honey Hill. Also, newspaper clippings re this battle, (1898-1899, 1914.) and an address delivered to the Confederate Survivors' Association, 1885., 1864, 1899, 1901, 1914-1917 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- The Battle of Honey Hill on Broad River, South Carolina., Nov. 30, 1864 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- The Battle of Pocotaligo. Deveraux's Neck, South Carolina., Dec. 9, 1864 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- 50th Anniversary of the Battle of Fort Wagner. (Newspaper clippings and broadsides.), July 18, 1913 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Fort Wagner - Evacuation and Occupation. (Newspaper articles and letters.), 1914 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Excerpt from a public address by Jefferson Davis threatening commissioned officers who might aid negroes or mulattoes., 1863 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Excerpts from the diary of Lieutenant Dennis Hartwell Jones; and a letter from Captain Charles Soule of the Massachusetts 55th Regiment re Jones' accidental death., 1863-1864 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Letters from Anna G. Pratt (wife of Captain Wheelock Pratt of the 55th Massachusetts Volunteer Regiment.), Aug.-Sept. 1914 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Excerpts from Civil War letters of Col. Charles Barnard Fox recorded by Burt Green Wilder., 1914 (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Letters and recollections of Major Charles Carroll Soule. (Including his obituary notices)., 1901-1914 (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Francis H. Brown, M.D., a prominent Civil War doctor, correspondence and biographic material., 1835-1917 (Box 5, Folder 21)
- William A. Hammond, M.D., Surgeon General of the United States, correspondence and biographic material., 1883, 1914 (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Joseph Trimble Rothrock, M.D. correspondence and biographic material, 1912-1916 (Box 5, Folder 23)
- Rev. James H. Fowler, Chaplain of the 33rd U.S. Black Troops and also a "citizen-nurse" at Judiciary Square in Washington, D.C., correspondence and biographic material, 1863-1864, 1910-1914 (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Nurses during the Civil War., 1907-1914 (Box 5, Folder 25)
- Doctors during the Civil War., 1914 (Box 5, Folder 26)
- Correspondence re Photographic History of the Civil War., Mar. 1913 (Box 5, Folder 27)
- Writings and Opinions of Burt Green Wilder., 1914-1919 (Box 5, Folder 28)
- Short Narratives re the Civil War., 1863-1878, 1914 (Box 5, Folder 29)
- Diagram of the Plan of Defences at "Yellow Bluff", now New Berlin, Florida, St. John's River. (Box 5, Folder 31)
- Chaplains in the Civil War., Oct. 1, 1914 (Box 5, Folder 30)
- Account of Robertson James at Grimballs' Causeway. (Robertson James was the brother of Henry James)., Feb. 10, 1865 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Battle of Grimball's Causeway on James Island., Feb. 10, 1865 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Letters (and some drawings and maps) of the Incident at River's Causeway and other reminiscences re this battle., 1863-1919 (Box 6, Folder 3)